Maine Acadian Cultural Survey Collection
American Folklife Center, Library of Congress
- Series 3: Graphic materials, The original materials are stored at Ft. Meade.
  - Color slides, 2380 color slides
    - Aerial photographs, St. John River Valley, Maine, July 25, 1991, AFC 1991/029: DW-C070; David A. Whitman; 20 35mm color slides
      These images are aerial photographs of various parts of the study area. The flight began at the airport in Frenchville, ME, headed east to Van Buren, proceeded north and west along the St. John River to Fort Kent, then south to Soldier Pond, and finally east over St. Agatha and back to the Frenchville airport; 1, Village Acadien; the buildings are said to be arranged in the shape of the letter A; 2, Farmland in New Brunswick; note the long lot pattern of the fields; 3, Village Acadien; 4-5, Forest and farmland in Maine, between Van Buren and Lille; 6-16, Our Lady of Mount Carmel Catholic Church and presbytery in Lille; 17-18, Grand Isle, ME; 19, Settlements on both the Maine (left) side and New Brunswick side of the river show typically French line settlement patterns; 20, St. David Catholic Church, St. David, ME.
    - Aerial photographs, St. John River Valley, Maine, July 25, 1991, AFC 1991/029: DW-C071; David A. Whitman; 20 35mm color slides
      These images are aerial photographs of various parts of the study area. The flight began at the airport in Frenchville, ME, headed east to Van Buren, proceeded north and west along the St. John River to Fort Kent, then south to Soldier Pond, and finally east over St. Agatha and back to the Frenchville airport; 1, St. David Catholic Church, St. David, ME; 2-3, Fred Albert house (just left of center) and Geraldine and Ernie Chasse house (red brick, green roof, just right of center); the Acadian Cross Historic Shrine is barely visible at the top; 4-8, Albert house, Chasse house, St. David Catholic Church; 9-12, Acadian Cross Historic Shrine, commemorating the Acadian landing site; 13-14, Edmunston, New Brunswick; the large industrial facility is Fraser Paper; 15, Madawaska, ME, looking south from over Edmunston; the Maine plant of Fraser Paper is in the center of the frame. The bridge to the left supports a pipeline connecting the Maine and New Brunswick Fraser facilities; 16-17, Edmunston; the confluence of the Madawaska and St. John Rivers can be seen on the left; 18, Settlement on both sides of the St. John just upriver from Madawaska and Edmunston; 19, A lake in New Brunswick, possibly Lac Baker; 20, Commercial buildings along the railroad tracks; most or perhaps even all of these are not in use.
    - Aerial photographs, St. John River Valley, Maine, July 25, 1991, AFC 1991/029: DW-C072; David A. Whitman; 20 35mm color slides
      These images are aerial photographs of various parts of the study area. The flight began at the airport in Frenchville, ME, headed east to Van Buren, proceeded north and west along the St. John River to Fort Kent, then south to Soldier Pond, and finally east over St. Agatha and back to the Frenchville airport; 1-3, Photos showing both strip settlement patterns along the river and commercial development along the railroad track, Frenchville, ME; 4-11, Eloi Daigle house, Fort Kent, ME; 12-16, Twin barn, Fort Kent, ME; 17, Assembly of God Church, Fort Kent; 18, Twin barn (same as 12-16); 19, St. Louis Catholic Church, Fort Kent; 20, Area of commercial development along the railroad tracks on Market St., Fort Kent; some shipping by rail still occurs from this area, as evidenced by the railroad cars.
    - Aerial photographs, St. John River Valley, Maine, July 25, 1991, AFC 1991/029: DW-C073; David A. Whitman; 20 35mm color slides
      These images are aerial photographs of various parts of the study area. The flight began at the airport in Frenchville, ME, headed east to Van Buren, proceeded north and west along the St. John River to Fort Kent, then south to Soldier Pond, and finally east over St. Agatha and back to the Frenchville airport; 1-2, Farmland and forest in Fort Kent; the pattern of roads and fields is suggestive of long lot land division, and much of this forest was probably once in farms; 3-8, Soldier Pond, ME; the large track-side potato house in the center of #6-8 belong to grower Herman Deprey of New Canada, ME; 9-10, Farmland in New Canada; the long lot patterns are clearly seen; 11, Forest, farm, and village form a mosaic; precise location unknown; 12-13, A twin barn in eastern Fort Kent; 14, This photo shows the line settlement pattern; just visible in the center of the frame is the Corriveau buckwheat mill in Frenchville, ME. The mill is not operating; 15-20, Corriveau mill (with tall chimney).
    - Aerial photographs, Upper St. John River Valley, Maine; Katherine "Kitty" Brown house, Wallagrass, Maine, July 25, 1991 - July 26, 1991, AFC 1991/029: DW-C074; David A. Whitman; 20 35mm color slides
      These images are aerial photographs of various parts of the study area. The flight began at the airport in Frenchville, ME, headed east to Van Buren, proceeded north and west along the St. John River to Fort Kent, then south to Soldier Pond, and finally east over St. Agatha and back to the Frenchville airport; 1, Corriveau buckwheat mill (with tall chimney), Frenchville, ME; the mill is not operating; 2-3, Strip of commercial development along railroad tracks in Frenchville; many of these are warehouse buildings which are no longer in use; 4-17, Farmland and the village of St. Agatha on the shore of Long Lake; the long lot patterns are clearly visible in the layout of the fields and roads; 18, The St. John River Valley, photographed just prior to landing at the Frenchville airport; 19-20, The house of Katherine "Kitty" Brown on State Highway 11 in Wallagrass; Ms. Brown is the mother of Phil Brown, owner of the camp on Eagle Lake occupied by fieldworkers Ray Brassieur and David Whitman. Ms. Brown's son, John, lives with her. The house was first we saw with this gray and red color scheme, which turned out to be a popular combination throughout the study area.
    - Houses near Eagle Lake, Maine; Home of Frances Gendreau, Madawaska, Maine, July 26, 1991 - July 27, 1991, AFC 1991/029: DW-C075; David A. Whitman; 20 35mm color slides
      A variety of scenes near Eagle Lake, ME; 1, House next to the home of Katherine Brown on State Highway 11; the red/brown trim is a color commonly used in the area; 2, Gray and red house on Eagle Lake; this color combination is frequently seen; 3, Typical partially buried potato house; this one, like many, is no longer used. The "Welcome to Beautiful Eagle Lake" sign stands in contrast to the abandoned barn; These images document a visit to the home of Frances Gendreau in Madawaska, ME; 4-5, Living room wall; the scene was painted by Ms. Gendreau's mother, Julie Albert. Stuffed owls were seen in several homes in the study area; 6-13, Stone tool which Ms. Gendreau said had been given to her by her uncle Fred Albert; he purportedly dug it up while plowing on his farm; 14-16, Small metal box, also given to Ms. Gendreau by Fred Albert; 17, Clay pipe from Fred Albert; Ms. Gendreau associated this pipe with a story her uncle told about smoking it with Indians; 18-20, Hand carved wooden book.
    - St. Agatha Catholic Church and other scenes, St. Agatha, Maine; Adrien Morin, potato and barrel maker, Saint David, Maine, July 27, 1991, AFC 1991/029: DW-C076; David A. Whitman; 20 35mm color slides
      A variety of scenes in St. Agatha, ME; 1-2, St. Agatha Catholic Church; 3, Monfort Heights, a former convent in St. Agatha converted to a residential facility for senior citizens; 4, Shrine over doorway, Monfort Heights; 5, Plaque on St. Agatha Catholic Church; 6, Church cornerstone; 7, Decorative stonework on church; 8, Babe's Water pump Service, St. Agatha, an example of how people in the study area have incorporated businesses into their homes; These images document a visit to Adrien Morin, a potato farmer and barrel maker in St. David, ME. Mr. Morin is one of the only remaining makers of wooden potato barrels, which were once used on a large scale for harvesting potatoes; 9-11, Adrien Morin shows field coordinator Ray Brassieur some of the equipment used to cut staves; 12, Equipment for making staves; 13-16, Equipment used in making wooden hoops. #15-16, Morin demonstrates some techniques to Brassieur; 17-18, Adrien's son Ray shows how a barrel is assembled; 19, Morin shows a finished barrel to Brassieur; 20, Ray Morin assembles a barrel.
    - Adrien Morin, potato grower and barrel maker, Saint David, Maine, July 27, 1991, AFC 1991/029: DW-C077; David A. Whitman; 20 35mm color slides
      These images document a visit to potato grower and barrel maker Adrien Morin in St. David, ME. See MAP-DW-C076 for more information; 1-4, Adrien's son Ray demonstrates how a barrel is assembled; the large wheel is turned to apply the necessary pressure on a band which forces the staves together; then, a hoop is slipped over the staves; 5, Equipment used in final assembly; 6-7, Finished potato barrels; 8-10, Field coordinator Ray Brassieur discusses the operation with the Morins; 11-12, see #5; 13, Building which houses part of the barrel making operation; 14, Morin's truck; 15-16, Sign for the barrel-making business; 17, A variety of trucks on the Morin farm; 18, The building in which staves are made; 19, Chair made from part of a barrel; 20, Painting of potato barrels in Morin's office; artist unknown.
    - St. Luce Catholic Church, Frenchville, Maine, July 27, 1991, AFC 1991/029: DW-C078; David A. Whitman; 20 35mm color slides
      These images (except #1) document St. Luce Catholic Church in Frenchville, ME; 1, Train car and water tower in Frenchville, restored and maintained by the Frenchville Historical Society; 2-3, Looking toward the altar from the back of the sanctuary; 4-5, Stations of the cross; 6, Statues of saints; 7, Pews; 8, Looking up at the ceiling in the sanctuary; 11-13, Columns and molding in the sanctuary; 15-16, St. Luce with plate of eyes; 17, Looking toward the back of the sanctuary; 18, Box in rear of sanctuary for offerings; 19-20, Texturized surface on exterior walls.
    - Various buildings and scenes, Frenchville, Maine; Wallagrass, Maine, July 27, 1991 - July 28, 1991, AFC 1991/029: DW-C079; David A. Whitman; 20 35mm color slides
      These images document a variety of buildings and scenes; 1-5, Wooden cross at senior citizen residential facility across the road from St. Luce Catholic Church, Frenchville, ME; close-ups in #2-4 show saw marks consistent with pit-sawn lumber; 6, Wrought iron representation of Virgin Mary on exterior wall of residential facility; 7, Presbytery at St. Luce Catholic Church; 8, Chrome ball, a popular yard ornament, Wallagrass; 9-12, A variety of decorative boards used on eaves of houses, Wallagrass; many different patterns of these boards are found throughout the study area; 13, Large rock in yard, Wallagrass; such rocks are often used as decorative items. This one is painted; some are landscaped, and some simply jut up from the yard; 14-15, Members of a group known as Rainbows at a rest area on State Highway 11, Wallagrass; 16, Pump for delivery of well water at rest area; 17, Kendo, a member of the Rainbows; 18-20, A shrine and grottoes at the Catholic church in Soldier Pond.
    - Catholic Church and houses, Soldier Pond, Maine; Various scenes, Eagle, Lake, Maine, July 28, 1991, AFC 1991/029: DW-C080; David A. Whitman; 20 35mm color slides
      These images document the Catholic church at Soldier Pond; 1-2, Grottoes; 3, Church; Miscellaneous scenes; 4-8, Decorative boards on eaves of houses in Soldier Pond; a variety of such boards are found throughout the study area; 9, Small building with facade attached to house in Soldier Pond, it appears to have once been a commercial building; 10-11, Decorative boards on eaves, Eagle Lake; 12, House in Eagle Lake; the gray and red color combination is a popular one throughout the area; 13-20, Sunset on Eagle Lake.
    - Landscapes scenes, Eagle Lake, Maine; Eloi Daigle house, Fort Kent, Maine, July 28, 1991 - July 29, 1991, AFC 1991/029: DW-C081; David A. Whitman; 20 35mm color slides
      An assortment of miscellaneous scenes on Eagle Lake; 1-4, Sunset on Eagle Lake, photographed from the deck of the camp occupied by fieldworkers Ray Brassieur and David Whitman; 5-6, Moon over Eagle Lake, from deck of camp; 7-8, Cloth bag with graphic depicting town of Madawaska, ME, available through Madawaska Chamber of Commerce; 9-15, Loons on Eagle Lake; These images document the Eloi Daigle house on U.S. Highway 1, Fort Kent, ME. This house has apparently been continuously occupied since its construction in the mid-nineteenth century; it is one of the oldest still standing in the area; 16-20, Eloi Daigle house; the unpainted section and garage represent much later additions.
    - Eloi Daigle house, Fort Kent, Maine; Ship's knee and Fred Albert house, Saint David, Maine; Various scenes, Frenchville, Maine, and Upper St. John River Valley, New Brunswick, July 29, 1991, AFC 1991/029: DW-C082; David A. Whitman; 20 35mm color slides
      These images document the Eloi Daigle house in Fort Kent, ME; see MAP-DW-C081 for more information; 1-3, Exterior of Daigle house; 4-9, Closet door in Daigle house; an interesting and typically Acadian feature is that the fancier chamfered panels are on the inside of the door; These images document a ship's knee in the Fred Albert house in St. David, ME. Other photo logs and field notes from this project contain a good deal of information about the Albert house and ship's knees; 10-12, Close-ups of ship's knee showing the heads of fasteners called drift pins; 13-15, Ship's knee connecting attic floor to top plate; Miscellaneous images; 16, Shrine on a porch in Frenchville, ME; such shrines are a common sight at houses throughout the study area; 17-18, Elroi Daigle house in Frenchville, ME, as seen looking across the St. John River from New Brunswick; 19, Memorial plaque in the upper Saint John River Valley, New Brunswick; 20, Sign advertising "Patates a vendre" (potatoes for sale), New Brunswick.
    - Various buildings and scenes, Wallagrass, Maine; Fort Kent, Maine; and Frenchville, Maine, July 30, 1991, AFC 1991/029: DW-C083; David A. Whitman; 20 35mm color slides
      These images document a variety of buildings and scenes; 1, Sign warning of railroad crossing on driveway leaving the camp on Eagle Lake occupied by fieldworkers Ray Brassieur and David Whitman? there was a recent fatality at this crossing; 2, Barn with completed shake shingle repair, Wallagrass, ME; 3, Barn designed and built by Paul Freeman in Wallagrass; 4, Paul Freeman's house; 5, Old schoolhouse being restored, probably to be used as a residence, Wallagrass; 6, Hay under a tarp at a farm on State Highway 11, Wallagrass; 7, House with flock of sheep in small fenced pasture, Wallagrass; 8, Plourde's Catering truck, Fort Kent, ME? the Plourdes run a small grocery store and catering business from their home; 9-10, Abandoned starch factory on the Fish River in Fort Kent, one of two such abandoned facilities in the area; the other is in Frenchville; 11, School bus garage in Fort Kent with a type of facade which is also found on residential property throughout the study area; 12-13, House on Highway 11, Fort Kent; the fresh coat of bright blue paint may indicate that bright greens and blues are enjoying renewed popularity in the area; 14-15, International bridge over the St. John River between Fort Kent, ME, and Clair, New Brunswick; 16, French sign at the DOC service station in Fort Kent; this sign, which changed often (sometimes daily) was in English throughout June and July; this message was posted on or about July 30; 17-18, Phillipe Roy Building, 1820, downtown Fort Kent; 19, First Assembly of God Church, Fort Kent; there seems to have been a recent increase in the number of Protestant churches in the predominantly Catholic study area; 20, Array of lawn ornaments, including penguins and chrome balls, Frenchville, ME.
    - Various buildings and scenes, Frenchville, Maine, and Fort Kent, Maine, July 30, 1991, AFC 1991/029: DW-C084; David A. Whitman; 14 35mm color slides
      Miscellaneous scenes; 1, Array of lawn ornaments, including pelicans and chrome balls, Frenchville, ME; 2, Barn well-known locally as the "Star Barn"; 3-4, Shrine at a house in Frenchville; 6, Train car loaded with logs, Frenchville; 7, Decorative pelican on a porch railing, Frenchville; 8-11, Farmland in New Brunswick, photographed from a rest area on U.S. Highway 1 in Frenchville; the layout of the fields suggests a long lot pattern of land division; 12-13, Frank's appliance repair, an example of the many different types of business which area residents have incorporated into their residences; 14, Alberie Pelletier's potato house on Market St., Fort Kent; Mr. Pelletier claimed that, of the group of potato houses along this stretch (there are several), this was the only one currently in use (as a potato house).
    - Scenes along U.S. Highway 1, Frenchville, Maine and Fort Kent, Maine; Grande Riviere Festival, Van Buren, Maine, July 13, 1991 - July 14, 1991, AFC 1991/029: DW-C085; David A. Whitman; 11 35mm color slides
      These images were inadvertently omitted during accessioning. In proper sequence, these would fall between MAP-DW-C046-4 and MAP-DW-C04 6-5; 1, Lit shrine, U.S. Highway 1, Frenchville, ME; 2, Collapsing twin barn, Maine Highway 161, Fort Kent, ME; 3-5, Harvesting new potatoes by hand; 6, Sign at a farm on Maine Highway 161; 7-11, Tintamarre, Grande Riviere Festival, Van Buren, ME.
    - In and around Eagle Lake, Maine; Maison Daigle St. Jean, Clair, New Brunswick, June 25, 1991 - June 26, 1991, AFC 1991/029: HM-C001; Howard W. Marshall; 20 35mm color slides
      These images document the Eagle Lake environs on June 25, and on June 26, field research in recording an 1848 French (Acadian) house in Clair, New Brunswick. This house (Maison Daigle St. Jean) is an important historic Acadian house that has been reconstructed as a museum site by the Clair Historical Society, Inc. See Marshall's fieldnotes for June 26; 1-7, Eagle Lake, early morning; views from front porch of the Phil Brown house (fieldworkers' lodgings); 8-16, Maison Daigle St. Jean: views of the house. This is a piece-sur-piece en colombage Acadian log house of the first quality. SEE fieldnotes. Note its massing, its ornament, and the front door area; 17, Brassier on the front porch; 18-20, Views of interior: kitchen. Note built-in cupboard and the niche for various religious statues representing the annual cycle of Catholic observances (here, Jesus).
    - Maison Daigle St. Jean, Clair, New Brunswick; St. John River, potato houses, railroad, Fort Kent, Maine, June 26, 1991, AFC 1991/029: HM-C002; Howard W. Marshall; 20 35mm color slides
      Continuation of Maison Daigle St. John; 1 Interior view of left front parlor; note boxed-in columns (this is a piece-sur-piece, en colombage house); 1848; 2, Maison Daigle St. Jean guide Ms. Nadine Caouette. Please send courtesy print to her, c/o the museum, Clair, NB; 3-4, the house with the new Acadian barn to its left and rear; this barn is a careful replica of the "grange Acadien" barn type that is representative of the early period of Acadian settlement and agricultural economy; 5, interior of second story of the house; note the ship's knee brace that is an important feature of these houses; 5-8, the grange Acadien here; #8 is Lisa Ornstein visiting with the museum builders/staff; 9-13, environs of the Maison Daigle museum; views working left to right of the St. John River and Ft. Kent, from shore of river adjacent to the Maison Daigle St. Jean site; 14-15, highway and sign for Maison Daigle museum, Clair, NB; 16, border customs check point, Canadian side; 17, view of St. John River form middle of the bridge between Clair, NB and Ft. Kent; note sign indicating international boundary; 18-20, potato houses and Bangor and Aroostook Railroad cars along Market Street in Ft. Kent, Me.
    - Buildings and various scenes, Fort Kent, Maine, and Eagle Lake, Maine, June 26, 1991, AFC 1991/029: HM-C003; Howard W. Marshall; 20 35mm color slides
      Continuation of Ft. Kent; Eagle Lake buildings; 1-13, potato houses on Market Street, beside Bangor and Aroostook Railroad tracks; railroad flat cars loaded with harvested logs to be shipped to regional lumber and paper mills; 11-13, show historic BAR depot beside tracks; 14-15, Acadian type house on corner of Dube St. and U.S. Hwy. 1, Ft. Kent; 16-17, farm: potato house of 20th century variety (partly subterranean), Maine highway 11 south of Ft. Kent at Wallagrass; 18, Acadian cottage (center) with attached additions, Ft. Kent, on Me. 11; 19, Eagle Lake post office; 20, retirement home, Ft. Kent.
    - Val Violette House, Van Buren, Maine, June 26, 1991 - June 27, 1991, AFC 1991/029: HM-C004; Howard W. Marshall; 20 35mm color slides
      The Val Violette House is an important Acadian dwelling, in the piece-sur-piece en colombage construction tradition, and on National Register of Historic Places; 1-2, "temple form" Greek Revival-influenced Victorian period farm house, on Maine 11 near Eagle Lake, June 26; 3, John Brown house, on Me. 11 across the highway from Phil Brown house (fieldworkers' lodgings); note its color scheme: "sang de beouf" (ox blood shade of red plus grey); this color scheme is important regional identity in the St. John valley; 4, USGS quadrangle map of field research, on office wall, Ft. Kent field headquarters; 13, views of Val Violette House, US 1, Van Buren; this is a large and expanded version of the 19th century Acadian cottage house type; piece-sur-piece / log construction with columns (en colombage); note Greek Revival cornice and pilasters and other stylistic period decoration details; 14, Ray Brassieur inspects pieces of the madriers (logs) left from a remodeling of the Violette House; note the shape and size of these logs that were horizontal logs set flush (piece-sur-piece construction); not the tenon on the end of the log that was let into the groove (coulisse) in the vertical column; 15-18, details of roof construction in Violette House; note joints, note original decking under roofing; 19, equipment found by Brassier in the attic with a loom; 20, Sisters visiting there: S. Ludwina Deveau (a nun) (rt.) and her sister, Sister Hermine Deveau (a Marist missionary) * SEND COURTESY PRINT OF THIS SLIDE TO THEM (RB has address).
    - Val Violette House, Van Buren, Maine; Houses, Madawaska, Maine, June 27, 1991, AFC 1991/029: HM-C005; Howard W. Marshall; 20 35mm color slides
      Continuation of Val Violette House; etc.; 1, Sisters visiting the Violette Hous; S. Ludwina Deveau (a nun) (rt.) and her sister, Sister Hermine Deveau (a Marist missionary); 2, DO, with Brassieur; 3-4, houses, Upper Frenchville; 5-7, Railroad water tank and caboose reconstructed by Frenchville historical society; 8-9, Frenchville Video Outlet and Jesse's Foodland (1-543-6011, Mr. Jesse Michaud, PO Box 225, Frenchville, ME 04745); the "square of the house" is a piece-sur-piece log Acadian cottage; compare with Plourdes Store, Soldier Pond (similar reconfiguring of Acadian house as a community grocery store); 10, house, Madawaska; 11, commercial building, Madawaska; 12-13, olive green Greek / neoclassical detailed vernacular house (central hall house type), Madawaska on Hwy. 246; 14-16, Brunswick Beverages / Aroostook Butter bldg., Hwy. 1, Madawaska; 17, Fred Albert house, Madawaska; 18, vinyl siding / natural wood pilasters, Greek vernacular house, west of Madawaska on US 1; 19-20, Soldier Pond rest stop, picnic area on Me. 11; interpretive sign about early roads to Ft. Kent (1839 Fish River Road, etc.).